okay all right great well thanks
everyone for coming welcome to the
awakening from the meaning crisis
discord Q&A we have a special guest
today Paul Vander clay who I I think
most of our members are probably
familiar with but I'll give a brief
introduction Paul is a pastor a minister
with the Christian Reformed Church of
North America his church is in
Sacramento California
he rose to prominence in in our
community and to to this type this
community starting with his YouTube
channel and his his videos on
surrounding Jordan Peterson and that
sort of ballooned and his channel is
exploded into this channel where he just
has just a plethora of amazing
conversations various guests and one of
his frequent talking companions is John
rebecky and so these two have formed a
friendship seems and and have some
amazing some amazing conversations that
probably people here are familiar with
both on on Paul's channel and on on
John's channel so and Paul has been kind
enough to come here today so thank you
Paul for being here we really appreciate
it it's my pleasure so maybe you can
just start off by telling us just a
little bit about yourself and about
yourself in your channel and your work
and and how you met John and the the the
relationship you two have have developed
over time okay well I've been a minister
in the Christian Reformed Church for a
few decades now I started off being my
father and my grandfather were both
ministers in the Christian Church after
college and seminary my first my first
post was in the Dominican Republic doing
missionary work and then after that I
came to Sacramento California and I've
been here for Wow it'll be 20
three years this August
about three years ago I began to notice
the work of jordan peterson and more
like four years ago now now three and i
became interested in him i had always
used a blog as sort of a conversation
partner i'm a solo pastor of a small
church and so finding people to talk
about the kinds of things I'm interested
in wasn't always easy so via a blog and
listservs and some other groups I would
always look for conversation partners
and then when Jordan Peterson arose
there are a lot of interesting things
about his work that I wanted to talk
about I had difficulty getting a lot of
other pastors interested in talking
about it and I was also reading Neil
postman at that time thinking about his
book amusing ourselves to death and
thinking about the medium of YouTube and
so I decided to make a youtube video and
whereas I had blogged for years and you
know there might my blog would usually
get maybe two or three hundred hits a
day the and that wasn't per that was the
entire blog ice began getting more
traffic to my YouTube channel and then
because I'm a pastor people wanted to
talk to me and one thing would lead to
another
I found that sharing some of these
conversations when appropriate was
helpful for people and the conversation
just continued to bloom along the way
and he's in the he's in the chat I
noticed here I can never quite say his
name right strong strong was one of the
people that was listening to me and he
would send me emails and he would send
me teas cut and paste these long
sections from Wikipedia about this
philosopher that philosopher and and he
was he was really working hard to
colonize me and he said well there's
this guy this other professor at
University of Toronto whose who has some
videos and you really have to watch his
videos and so that was John and I okay
but a lot of people send me videos and
so it's always hard to know what's gonna
sort of get to the top of the the
salience hierarchy but I watched some of
them and the sound was kind of
annoyingly bad which I really don't have
reason to point point fingers have
there's bad sound and plenty of my
videos but I there was there was enough
there that really caught my interest and
I had used him a couple of times in some
of my videos trying to feel out who he
is at a very low resolution idea of who
he was and then he started doing
awakening from the meaning crisis where
the sound was for the most part very
good and he was laying out things in a
systematic form and I began following
him in a more disciplined way and really
discovered some some really helpful
ideas and terminology just helped me
understand philosophy better and figure
out what cognitive science was learn all
of this stuff better and then John you
know I noticed had been made some
comments and some of the videos that I
had commented on him and he had sent me
an email and said you know I'd like I'd
love to do a conversation and I said
that'd be great and so that sort of has
has continued on and yeah a friendship I
you know as he offer he says I have a
lot of affection for Palo I have a lot
of affection for John and we haven't
been able to meet in person yet that
we've we've chatted online and we
chatted via email so I'm I'm fearful
that the much-anticipated conference
coming up in fun planned for Thunder
battle Thunder Valley that's a casino
here Thunder Bay Ontario where myself
and Jonathan pezzo and John Verve a key
could all get together and have a
conversation
I fear because of Koba that might not
happen but I very much a Lord willing
anticipate meeting John in person at
some point and hopefully our friendship
over the years can deepen I owe him a
tremendous debt the the longer ice
with his with his work awakening from
the meaning crisis the more I'm
impressed by it
the deeper my learning comes you know
one of the things that you quickly
realize as you open up your circles to a
bigger vein like YouTube there are a lot
of smart people out there and I'm not
necessarily at the top of the hierarchy
and ideas take time to sink in it's it's
fairly difficult to colonize a
50-something year-old man and and so the
idea sink in and through my monologue
videos you can tell how he keeps coming
up and as he's often said he one of the
things he did with awakening from the
meeting crisis is he at least in this
little corner of the Internet has helped
standardize a degree of language and
giving and giving me some base tools
with which to continue to pursue my work
you know his four p's lately I've been
thinking a lot about cognitive science
and you know probably dealing with
problems what problems are why we have
them so lots of things and so I've you
know I've benefitted tremendously from
John's work and I'm very excited about
you know have continuing to have
personal conversations with him and you
know he's extremely generous with his
engagement and and so it's just been a
joy and so I was really thrilled to see
this discord server after learning about
that because of the guys over at bridges
of meaning and so coming here today is
just a pleasure great so we we
definitely owe thanks to strong for for
introducing you to John and and by the
way Nick Nick Bea's one of the
moderators on your bridges of meaning
server helped coordinate this this
meeting today so so thank you Nick for
that I'll just throw one last question
so so you're you're a Christian pastor
and John is a non theist who's you know
talking about creating the religion
that's no
religion and so that makes it an
interesting contrast how what are your
feelings about what are your thoughts
about the religion that's not a religion
and how do you how do you how do you
what do you think of it how do you
integrated into your thinking and you
know how do you do is there a conflict
there between yeah did you do you have
any cop conflicting thoughts about it
well I I think Mary cohan who runs a
channel she's a for a while she was a
Jehovah's Witness and she became a Roman
Catholic um very smart woman who is
doing some videos on Joseph Ratzinger
and chickens and a bunch of other things
I think in one of her she's had a number
of conversations with John as well as
well as JP Marceau who was a friend of
it was a friend of Jonathan pezzo and
quite active in his community
he's a pan cyclist and a Roman Catholic
and so for me my my vistas have simply
been broadened by all of this
interchange now you know before when
before we started the thing and we got
together and you called John an atheist
I sort of tried to gently correct you
he's a non theists and I I think a lot
of what's been helpful about John's work
he's up to the resolution on our
conversations and an on and you know
through my
to three years my whole project has just
really been a learning project for me
and I've gotten better acquainted with
some of the philosophical history with
Christian theology it's it's interesting
to me the amount of distance between
John's non-theism especially with his
interest and knowledge of neoplatonism
of Augustan versus my theism that gap
might not be as small as we it might not
be as large as we think it's and a lot
of my conversations with John and in
fact a video I'm planning to make this
afternoon
probably post it tomorrow has a lot to
do with this idea of person what is a
person and strong can of course talk a
lot about that but in a lot of ways the
the theism and non-theism gets down to
this question of personhood and what's
the what's the nature of the universe
where does consciousness fit in now
John's religion that's not a religion I
think is a recognition that throughout
history religious structures and
practices and communities and
perspectives have afforded tremendous
amounts of suffering that have helped
people on Jordan in a sort of Jordan
Peterson Peter Sounion way endure the
sufferings of life in this world and
whereas you know one of the biggest
differences let's say between John's
perspective and let's say the other
little side of Arc the the bisection of
our little corner of the internet say
that where Jonathan Pozzo and I reside
is that John is skeptical that the
Ecology's of practice and the community
structures and the worldviews and the
philosophy of Christianity can continue
to let's say not just endure or or face
a declining retreating posture in the
corners of culture but can in fact
energize and continue to be vital and
going into the future and I completely
understand John's perspective on this
because there have been many ways in
which the last 200 or so years certain
aspects of Christianity have been under
crisis stressed retreating sometimes
this is phrased as Charles Taylor does
as a subtraction story that and and John
is sophisticated enough and honest
enough
not to you know pull any fast moves or
low blows or cheap shots and one of the
things that you immediately begin to see
if you interact with John is he is a man
of integrity and he is he does have
conversations in good faith and his
whole project centers around the idea
that people with differences of opinions
can have a deal logos with each other
see I'm using these fancy Verve a
keywords as Jobe calls them could have a
deal logos with each other and both come
away from the conversation better for it
even if you know a significant aspect of
their kind of their disagreement let's
say theism versus non theism endures and
so John I Anjaana have found just a a
wonderful conversation partner and
teacher who has showed me so much and so
his as Mary Kohan said hey um would I
like people to come to Christianity and
use Christian practices and worldview in
theology absolutely that's part of my
profession it's part of my tradition
it's part of my Creed but I recognize
that at least in the short term that's
probably not going to happen and will
people find will people find rest for
their souls in some of the practices and
communities and ecology of practices
that he is promoting well it's not in my
power to stop that and I don't have an
interest in stopping it and so let's
continue the dialogue and let's continue
the conversation and again I thought
Mary who is nobody's gonna question her
credentials as a bona fide conservative
Roman Catholic you know she says hey if
people are getting helped by this okay
and I agree with Mary so we'll have some
differences but I'm I'm very interested
in the project and you know I want to
continue to follow along and be in
community with
people who are pursuing his project so
we can continue to learn together that's
excellent and and I should say you know
the the focus on communication I think
is critical and it's one of my focuses
to the the ability of people with
different beliefs and backgrounds to
communicate with each other to to you
know engage one another to to understand
one another and treat each others
respectfully and and similarly well
while still disagreeing I think that's
that's that's key and I think your your
talk certainly exemplify that so so
thank you for that so I'd like to open
it up to some questions now just please
note we are recording this session and
there is an awakening for the meaning
crisis discord YouTube channel and so
the next day or so we will be uploading
this to that I I think so my name is
Brett pleasure of doubt maybe if when
you ask question you could because it's
audio only you could state your name I
don't think we've been doing that but
that probably makes for a better
listening experience for people so if
you could state your name when when you
ask your question so who has a question
for Paul I pull mister on how are you
I'm good and you I have doing fine okay
so my question for you is are you gonna
join the server this could be an
excellent opportunity for you to pick up
some art with unwitting Christian strata
that I have talked a lot actually we
should let people know that that um I'm
glad that he's mysterious I'm glad that
he's more active now for a long time I
encouraged him I said you got to get out
there you've got a lot to contribute so
I'm really pleased to see you pursuing
this so anyway go ahead
I'm just trying to derail your question
because you're probably gonna ask me a
stumper so go right ahead no I thought I
already did are you going to join the
server and pick up some unwitting
Christians oh that's my question I I did
join yeah I haven't participated in it
much.i that's just been sort of a matter
of both economy of time and salience
hierarchy I owe a debt I think to the
bridges of meaning server and so that
tends to be where I hang out more but I
haven't really spent a lot of time here
to sort of poke around and I don't find
discord to be a terribly easy interface
and so we've been talking with my frie
do a Friday question and answer over at
the bridges of meaning and we've talked
about a week II or do some other things
to try to organize some of this so that
when people come in they can have
something what part of why I like the
and then growing an appreciation for the
discord servers is that they do tend to
facilitate community in a cyber way that
if the culture is healthy you know I
people sort of begin by they might see
me on YouTube they might watch a video
they might want a level of community and
I want there to be a place where they
can go now as a Christian pastor in this
practice in meatspace there's a church
and so if I meet somebody and we have a
good conversation I can say well you can
come to my church and meet more people
now since the jordan peterson thing i'll
say come to my local meetup and i've
been trying to help other meetups start
here on the west coast and in the united
states and canada but of course Kovan
has sort of sort of put a damper on that
for now
so yes i but it all depends on time so
that's sort of where I'm at yeah I will
say we've also put quite a bit of
thought into how we can arrange this
discord server so that it functions due
to both the community so yeah maybe you
can actually network on only ideas there
if we can't convey some wisdom anyway
thanks Paul yep and and it's really hard
for me to I'm it's Tron's contribution
to my work his I've just so enjoyed him
as a conversation part
Turner and he's I mean I wouldn't be
here if it weren't for him and his
effort so you know really my hats off to
him yeah maybe we'll all be very kind
make a little spot for him here we we
love him a little philosopher laureate
or something but there's I think there's
an element to the the community here
that I'd love to see unfold where it is
more easy and comfortable for us to
maneuver through these various spots and
these various modes of thinking and try
to learn from one another and I would
love to be able to see it one day where
these people that were learning to trust
to give us their perspective on the
world kid could move freely amongst the
communities and they that like these
kinds of conversations could happen
spontaneously and be as profitable and
it's enriching as we could make them
because I it truly is I think as you're
saying that collaborative effort when
you find somebody worthwhile to talk to
and when you find that they have
something real and true to say about the
world it makes all the difference so I I
guess I I really appreciate what this is
what you what you do with regards to the
work and sharing all this stuff and I'd
like to see it available to as many
people as possible so that's it's not a
question you guys thank you in school
Paul I already asked so this is Nick by
the way I already I already asked you
this question on on the Q&A in the
fridge is a winning server but I figured
it would probably fit well in here
seeing as from your discussion wait for
baekje won at one point in your guys's
conversation John gives an argument for
a pluralistic take take wronged religion
to which you you assented and when you
answer before you said that there was
actually a bit of a history of
pluralistic thinking within your
tradition he's wondering if maybe you
could go more again to that and in what
sense that pluralism work works and how
its kind of afforded within your your
world I knew as I said on the previous
one I knew when I knew when I said I
thought oh this is gonna get interesting
in terms of because the question of
pluralism is obviously a Christians
follow a master that says I am the way
the truth and the life no one comes to
the Father except by me that that tends
to narrow things for Christians at the
same time at the same time I was I was
thinking in my mind and I was answering
the question about the work of Abraham
Kuyper
now I grew up in the Christian Reformed
Church which is a small denomination
that historically was founded by Dutch
immigrants and in fact the pool of Dutch
immigrants were abnormally drawn from
kind of the lower-class secessionist
churches in the Netherlands that had two
major secessions from the Dutch state
church at the end of the 19th and
beginning of the 20th century two
dominant lights arose Herman bobbing
was a theologian primarily and Abram
Kuiper who was a kind of a polymath
theologian Abram Kuiper would go on to
found what would become the free
University in the Netherlands and free
meaning not no tuition but free meaning
disconnected from the state church he
would he would eventually become prime
minister of the nation and found some
practices which some in my tradition
called principled pluralism where
politically in terms of that politically
that would that would bear fruit in what
would be called polarization where Roman
Catholics could have their pillar Dutch
Reformed could have their pillar
modernists could have their pillar and
and the idea was that these communities
could continue to grow and develop and
hopefully be in conversation with each
other now kuiper also had the
distinction of also promoting what he
would call the antithesis which would
very much emphasize that word of Jesus I
am the way the truth of the life no one
comes to the Father except by me and
bring the antithesis way down into
theology into some very narrow ways and
so with kuiper you had this sort of both
and which both attempted to recognize
the antithetical nature of reality
either/or but also began to appreciate
and leave space for both and and that's
even though in the United States outside
of let's say Dutch Reformed and even
some neo evangelical circles
who would recognize the name of Abram
kuiper that has led to a posture in the
Christian Reformed Church the Christian
Reformed Church I think in some ways has
really tried to hold both sides of this
dialectic together where okay we we
believe what Jesus says is true and on
the other hand
understand that by virtue of let's say a
Calvinist appreciation for total
depravity none of us see clearly and
what that means is that I get many more
things wrong than I get right I should
afford that same generosity towards my
neighbors and the people with whom I
want to have conversation so this sort
of yields in the American context
freedom of religion and so it's I am NOT
interested in you know burning John
verve a key at the stake because he's a
non-theist I'm not interested in burning
Sam at the stake because he's deficient
in his Trinitarian views that Sam from
the bridges of meaning so let's continue
to talk together and appreciate what we
can about what other sides get right and
let's have this deal logos and learn
from each other and I think Jesus also
bears witness to this in the way in
which he promoted and pursued his goals
and my favourite example of that is the
unauthorized exec Exorcist which I often
like in Jordan Peterson to where there's
this guy running around delivering
people from demons in Jesus name and the
disciples want to enforce their
intellectual property and say Jesus
should we make him stop and Jesus says
leave him alone and so I think
Christians should on one hand be the
most secure in what they believe but on
the other hand also the most generous
and and that generosity flows out of the
security and my questions about other
things that God allows in other ways
that God works flows out of the security
that I am in his hand and so I think
these things that are feel some ways
antithetical actually work together
that's great thank you Paul you know
like
reminds me a little bit of Chester's
tins orthodoxy and talking he talks a
lot about her did paradoxes and how they
actually kind of fit together um I
bought my name is Eric Mike I've been
thinking a lot about what draws people
to religion and like what needs do they
want filled from it and I was talking to
my dad this weekend he was a Mormon
missionary for two years and so he
talked to a lot of people about this and
he came up with these like five
different reasons I'm curious to hear
your take on them one of them is
community I think that one's talked
about a lot one of them is like the
ritual and then there's the kind of
putting your trust in some authority
there's the kind of having a logical
understanding of what the cosmos is it
and what our place is in it and the
fifth one was spirituality and I'm also
curious if your what your take is on my
feeling that most mainstream Christians
and religions in general don't really
actually address the spirituality they
just mostly address the other aspects
that's a great list I just I just I just
typed it and I'm gonna keep it and I'm
gonna use it
pastors are thieves and if you if you
trot a really good idea out in front of
one he's gonna take it and run with it
so I hope I hope you I hope you see that
as the highest form of flattery for your
father's idea I think it's I think it's
a great list and I think well here's a
here's a so spirituality I actually
that's gonna be the topic of I'm gonna
go into that quite a bit in the video
that I hope to record this afternoon
what do we mean by spirit well I think
in some ways one of the areas in which
the word has not been fragmented and
degraded is if we use it for an example
like school
spirit we all understand that when you
were in school when you you had class
spirit your own class had a spirit about
it
that the teachers knew oh the class of
2018 is this way the class of 2019 was
that way individuals participated in
that spirit nobody controlled that
spirit that spirit was subject to
influence and and again so much of Verve
akise work I found helpful this kind of
opponent processing ideas all of John's
work is sort of this middle space
between you know between heaven and
earth let's say and here I'm gonna rip
off and Christianize bunch of John's
work and I'd find it nothing but
flattering if he does the same thing to
me
so spirituality has to do with the
question what makes the what makes the
tree move when I can't see the wind and
and Jesus Jesus uses this and uses this
illustration in John 3 where nobody
knows where the spirit comes from and
where the spirit blows what we we just
sort of see its effects now I think the
LDS Church the apart of the reason it's
been enormous ly successful
evangelistically is because it gets a
bunch of these things right community
ritual Authority now I'd have some
disagreements with it on world view but
spirituality has to do with what are the
what are the what are the ways in which
we influence and participate in the
molding of this layer of reality that we
can't fully control
we're subject to its influence we have
influence within it but in that way it's
sort of a space and I would say that
churches do better or worse and churches
do better or worse in this space and I
think the rise of Pentecostalism
is
a is a reaction both it's a reaction to
the meaning crisis it's a reaction to
modernity but if Luke from the bridges
of meaning channel we're here and the
randos it's also a reaction to as I
think Jonathan or John has noted many
times the out the imbalance of the
propositional in terms of the four PS as
they're working in religions and so
spirituality so you have got in
Christianity and the Trinity of God the
Father God the Son and God the Holy
Spirit the Spirit is often for modernist
theologians the most difficult member of
the Trinity to talk about and whereas
even with a theologian like John Calvin
who actually places a great deal of
emphasis on the work of the Holy Spirit
the Holy Spirit is vital in terms of
John Calvin's many have noted that well
Calvinist churches at least until John
Wimber and the vineyard movement
Calvinists churches did really poorly at
manifesting or appreciating the work of
this spirit so I think as modernism
continues to ebb we're going to see
probably continued growth in this area
and in terms of the LDS tradition you
know that one of the things that's true
about the LDS tradition is that it's
it's a prophetic tradition in which so a
lot of what I know about the elder law
church Jesus Christ of latter-day saints
I've learned from this homeless man that
sleeps outside my door who there's a
restraining order against but that are
you that from me but from the church
building so anyway that's a long story
but you know he was a dyed-in-the-wool
Mormon and I've learned a ton from him
about LDS Church in its history and and
the role that prophecy plays and so on
that said
the LDS Church in terms of that list of
five things is probably more open to
spirituality than let's say my tradition
of Calvinism thanks
very interesting would you um so just to
clarify would you do you associate
spirituality with the participatory
knowing or with a more of a balance
between them all oh that's a really good
question
definitely participatory definitely
procedural definitely perspectival and I
think I think probably Wade I we get
into a lot of trouble and and I've
noticed this and this is this is this
has shaped a lot of my life and I got
this from my father because my father
was also very high in openness but like
me born into a conservative dutch
reformed tradition and and one of the
things I learned from my father was he
always said you know be careful about
saying more than you know now this when
he uses knowledge in that sense are
traditionally we very much tie that to
propositional and in a modernist
framework you know when you listen to
sam harris talk he's very he's very much
propositional and so i think in some
ways
yeah spirituality is this really nuanced
this nuanced dance between the other
three and the propositional sort of has
to mind its place where the other three
are dancing in that way oh my god thanks
for time yep hi hello Paul
who's talking
it's pilgrim okay Pedro nice to meet you
thank you
to meet you too you know I was raised a
Christian but with time I kind of
drifted away from it and my question to
you is what is a way you would advise
someone to rediscover Christianity are
there readings you would advise and
spiritual practices something like that
I you know CS Lewis for me has I'm
taking notes now so I can because I
think this conversation goes well I'll
probably use it for my channel CS Lewis
for me has been sort of a mentor and I
think in many ways CS Lewis walked the
paths that we are walking almost a
hundred years before us because he was
raised in the Anglican Church his mother
died when he was six he by the time he
was a teenager
he was an angry atheist and his is
running through Anglican boarding
schools did not help him but hurt him
and he in many way that he went through
World War one survived it I mean he had
one heck of a meaning crisis and he had
to find his way out of it and so as
Jonathan pazzo pazzo said you know in
terms of great storytellers in the West
at least in the in the english-speaking
world we've got Tolkien and Lewis
Tolkien never left the faith although
someone mentioned in the comment that
his parents were Methodists so that's
interesting that you know he went back
towards a more sacramental tradition
Lewis tried to talk about mere
christianity where he said you know all
of these there's mere christianity as
this hallway and each of the traditions
are rooms off of it i I think for
someone who as you've described and
obviously if we had a longer
conversation we'd go further into the
details which is why I do these
conversations on my channel although I
don't have time for it
I think I think you have to sort of
follow your salience Lance Lance you
know your salience landscape and I think
and and because your mind is you are
working on stuff that your conscious
self doesn't know about and I think
peterson spoke eloquently about a lot of
these dynamics and and you have to
figure out well what what ideas what
corners of my consciousness congress
need addressing now i think finding a
church finding a member of the clergy or
a small group or a friend or a mentor
would be tremendously helpful in this
and I think mentors can be found dead or
alive
and so CS Lewis for me as a mentor tole
keen as a mentor I think John Verve a
key in many ways is a mentor for me he's
taught me so many things there are also
been pastors in my life my father of
course one but Dave Beale and it was a
pastor of mine and in college and
seminary taught me a ton Dante Venegas
and so I think look around for
communities and groups and mentors who
can and and I think it's it's
follow your interests because something
is is coming up on your salience
landscape for a reason well figure out
what that reason is and pursue it and
but I think there's no substitute for
finding a church and and be and I often
frame that as training the elephant so
you're so kind of the Jonathan height
representation of the rider and the
elephant the rider up there is chatty
deals and propositional truths the
elephant is much more majors on the
other piece and what getting involved in
terms of practice regular disciplined
practices corporate worship liturgy
prayer studying of the Bible all of
these
throughout the history of Christianity
have been ways in which people have we
have this Trites phrase becoming a
Christian well I've never stopped
becoming a Christian my whole life and I
don't suspect I will I think that we'll
go to the grave and maybe even beyond
thank you Paul I really appreciate your
answer
Chandra Vicki really is someone I find a
mentor right now and you know I'm gonna
explore the works of CS Lewis definitely
to start and well I really appreciate I
really appreciate it thank you thank you
um sure it's about you know when I
listen to John's talks it seems like his
core axiom is this idea that we can no
longer live in the two worlds mythology
and I haven't listened to all your
videos unfortunately but I don't know if
that's a door like how you address that
because I think that's you know if if I
were to have a criticism of John that
would be I'm the core obvious one he
starts from that premise and moves
everything forward so I just wondered
what your thoughts were on that yeah
well you know two worlds mythology is a
fairly low-resolution term that maps on
to a lot and I am also suspicious that
the two worlds mythology isn't going to
be easily dispensed with now I
appreciate John's work in this area and
again his point I mean the the kind of
the D key difference between sort of the
the way our corner of the Internet has
been bisected between let's say theists
and non-vegans
that the point that he makes about the
vigor in which the modernist scientific
achievements have
undermined previous theologies and
philosophies and spiritualities of
Christianity there's too it's simply
dishonest to under appreciate that truth
because one feels timid or insecure
about the the sunk costs in their own
religious tribe okay but to world's
mythologies perfect in the imperfect
antithetical verses of binary versus
analog there are all these dualities
some of which so nicely map on to the
two worlds mythology and the tube the
world's mythology is simply so handy at
at migrating so many of these dualisms
um I think it's just gonna be so darn
handy we can't get rid of it it kind of
like there's this somebody in the
bridges of meaning server put this
cartoon Morty and whatever I don't
that's not versed in these guys but um
Marty but anyway it's this this guy in
this kid and this kid was using a level
and the guys like flat you know you
don't know flat and then he goes and he
you know does all this stuff to create a
space in his floor that is perfectly
flat because gosh that level that you
know water and a bubble and a couple of
lines you're gonna judge level by that
well I think in many ways to low to
world's mythology is the bubble and the
water and the lines and it's just too
darn handy for regular people to use and
to map so many things on so I don't
think it's going away and you know and I
don't think it's going away it's like
it's like the level it might be a low
resolution instrument but it's so darn
handy it's gonna keep finding usefulness
wow that was a really good answer yeah I
sort of dude it is the
in the Jesus and sneaking in the science
myself but actually I like your
conception better of it as a tool that's
already adaptive and and it just has a
deeper meaning than what we're giving it
short to call it you know to world
mythology thank you
so Paul on that subject of the Holy
Spirit could you take a minute to take
some of the fuzziness out of how Rory
grace and the Holy Spirit or yeah that's
tangled up and how maybe you can
untangle a little bit well first take
everything I said about spirit and think
again about school spirit there's no way
you're gonna talk about school spirit
without Mountains of fudge
you know it's is it the design of the
building yes is it whether this the
school is in sunny California or
cloud-covered Western Michigan or
lowlands Europe yes is it is it whether
you know someone who looks like a
supermodel became a cheerleader and
started dating a guy who would become
Tom Brady yes does it has to do with
that nerdy history teacher that somehow
gives everybody an appetite for a
subject that many people flee yes
there's so much to it that and and again
this is where I think cognitive science
and the work of Jordan Peterson has been
tremendously helpful to me and if you
again you look at the jordan Peterson
versus sam harris debates but where i
think sam harris the longer i think
about those debates was just completely
exposed by those debates as not
keeping up with the conversation and the
struggle which we are seeing as human
beings which is that we are very small
and the world is very big and the kinds
of tools we use we need a lot of lossy
compression schemes like JPEG a lot of
lossy compression schemes in order to
take a world and a reality that is so
rich and now now we're now we're barking
on the door of glory not getting on the
dog barking at the door knocking on the
door knocking on the door of glory
because part of what makes this world so
rich is in fact the and and I think
Verve a key and some of his last videos
about in awakening from the meeting
crisis touched on this you know this
this space between the infinite and the
finite this and in my last conversation
with him the the more Ness virtues
versus suchness right in that space we
begin to taste glory but what glory is I
think in some ways is is where it all
comes together when we're right over at
that edge staring into the infinite and
we get the sense of wow and and so when
the when the when the Tom Brady and the
supermodel hook up there's like there's
something there we all envy and hate
them perhaps and maybe they're jerks but
there's something there and when the
history teacher nerd somehow teaches
history in such a way that people come
out of that class wanting wanting more
and the beautiful thing about history is
that we keep making more of it well
there's you know glory is in a sense
where the morning and the suchness meet
and we get an inkling of the
combinatorial explosiveness okay so here
we have the holy spirit which is
something we're not going to reduce
anytime soon so it's gonna be worlds of
fuzziness
and we have glory which is where more
nests and suchness meet and
you know why is glory always connected
with light well what is light light is
when all of you know we use a prism to
refract light and see its components
well white light is when all of the
components are there and they're all
there integrated and harmoniously and we
get a sense with light that it's
overwhelming to us because our eyes can
only take so much of it and our being
can only take so much of it so now we
have glory now we have the holy spirit
and now you want to talk about grace
well grace is in some ways the space
where tiny creatures can taste glory and
not have it overwhelm us and and
Christianity has worked this in lots of
different ways but the word grace
encompasses the more nests and the
suchness to you and that's where let's
say now I'll do some riffing on John
Calvin's theology for John Calvin the
the Holy Spirit was the applier and
grace was that which was applied so that
glory can be seen and tasted and what
that does in us is instill within us a
motivation and a crisis because what
glory does is on one hand gosh I want
more on the other hand oh I can't take
it and if you go back and you I think it
was well I was at Charles Finney or no
what's the what's the conservative
school and anyway he was a he was a
Christian who Christians every now and
then and I'm not going to talk about
others because I don't know and I used
the Jordan Peterson move
I know Christianity okay and there are
moments when Christians are in a sense
visited by God and and you know Pascal
had this and after he died they found
sewn in one of his favorite pieces of
clothing this you know this thing about
fire and it was moody I think it was
Dwight Moody
it was moody or Finny who had this
experience once where God came upon him
and and as so often happens with this
people say Lord if you don't let off of
me you'll destroy me well that's sort of
when the Holy Spirit and glory and grace
grace is in some ways the eyedropper
that administers the exact right amount
of the conjunction of Morna sand
suchness to us so that it leads us on a
path where we're going to go further up
and further in hey Paul it's Jacob
stalking you again I wanted to ask you
specifically regarding the religion
that's not a religion like I think most
people would say that central to
religion is the idea of God what does
the god idea add to all the non religion
religions non-theistic philosophies that
we've been trying to find meaning in who
and you know one of the things that over
these last three years that I've learned
a lot about has been and really what's
what was exposed in my theological and
philosophical deficiencies was what do
we mean by this little three-letter word
god that that you know the the Jewish
tradition quite rightly warned us
against taking lightly I sort of like
what I said about the two worlds
mythology I think the same way about the
God idea it's just
- darn handy and if there's one and John
and I have talked about this and John
has mentioned it as a pastor who now is
third-generation practitioner in the
meaning crisis is a very old thing I
think it comes in waves
so third-generation practitioner in
working on the front lines of the
meaning crisis I think the idea of God
is simply too useful and scalable an
idea that it's simply not going to be
dispensed with
philosophers with their big brains and
careful distinctions can do all kinds of
things of trying to describe it or avoid
it or or imagine the absence of it but I
think what we're seeing in real time is
that philosophers are only a small
segment of godsgarden of human beings
and if you're actually going to
religions for as long as we've known
human civilizations have been addressing
have been helping people and so you know
and yes there are some Eastern
traditions where God isn't you know well
there's non God and I think even the
distinction between a theism and
non-theism demonstrates it's just too
it's just too strong of an idea it's not
going anywhere and that's again part of
the reason the scalability issue why I'm
I'm convinced that Chesterton with his
seven deaths of should memorize that
title of that chapter seven deaths of
the faith I think he's right I weird
there's a reason you know when I was
reading I started looking at Plato's
Republic because I was reading the
divine conspiracy Dallas Willard's book
Dallas Willard was a professor of
philosophy at University of Southern
and he was making some connections
between play-doh and the Sermon on the
Mount so I I wanted to look at Plato's
Republic in the Greek and so I bought it
and then I began to notice that Plato
had Socrates talk about the gods and
talk about God and it's like what does
Plato mean when he uses God
singular what did Plato mean what he
used when contemporary editors would
rightly use gods with a lowercase G and
God with a capital G it ain't going away
and I think so that's I I don't I I'm
comfortable with my career choice Apollo
we've gone an hour I want to be
respectful of your time are you okay -
keep on going or I'm okay - keep on
going anybody watches my channel knows
you know I could sit for a while and
talk sure great well we'll have you as
long as as long as you want to be here
I'll tell you that so so that's that -
now we're from now in your yes yes I've
got another hour okay great
who has a question
you're breaking up I can't hear you you
could type it in the chat - in the event
listening party text you can type your
question there if you've got problems
with your mic all right well golden is
it's trying to try to fix that he's
typing so someone else can that can go
don't be shy that maybe we don't have
two hours worth of questions you talked
about sin as a future versus of think
about these religions without religion
does it strike you they're trying to
adjust the human iniquity or dissonance
as future well it's a really good
question see there's a reason pastors
don't do these question and answers
because you ask us really hard questions
they can get us in trouble
I think in Christianity ultimately it is
God that deals with sin and sin is both
transgression which is like rebellion
and can sometimes be missing the mark
which is you know perhaps not so willful
failing to achieve the potential that
God gave us and desires for us the the
line between those two things is
obviously a normative line now one of
the things I'm deeply indebted to dr.
Jim the cardiologist from Idaho was
introducing me to Wilfrid Sellars and
Daniel bond evacs
video where he lays out the difference
between the manifest and the scientific
image the different
between the manifest of the scientific
image in some ways maps on to this
question because the difference between
them is normativity science can tell you
what is the manifest image says what
should be and this weird space of this
is gonna get strong so excited this
weird space of potential and not meeting
up with one's potential it's not quite
clear where to map that on to in the
manifest versus scientific image
framework and and whenever you have
items like this that can't be easily
mapped on to them they cause dissonance
and so one of the now so a religion
that's a religion that's not a religion
is a really clever way of trying to get
at some things well what are we trying
to get at and now over my videos over
the last few weeks a couple of months
I've been really working on this
question of religiosity and so when when
John Verve a key says an economy of an
ecology of practice well a religious II
word for that is ritual and when we talk
about community a religious a religious
E word for that is church and so okay so
we're trying to create something that
will not have the observed deficiencies
and limitations of the items that are
already on the spirituality market and
and so you know in this way you know
whereas someone might come to me and say
Oh Paul you should be you shouldn't be
down for John's work with this religion
that's not a religion no because I
understand this the good faith in which
John is practicing and I think that
what John learns when when John
addresses the deficiencies that he's
seen in religion well look at my first
video with John who is John reveille
Qian what is he and what is the meaning
crisis you know why do I when I
interview people want to take some time
to dig into their story because the more
nests and the suchness of John verve a
key come together in this project and
the crazy thing about human beings is
very little is wasted and if you expand
this into Christian ecclesiology I might
argue that perhaps theoretically oh gosh
now I have just triggered universalism
very little is wasted in terms of you
know John's story and his the the
reasons why he looks at religion and
says ah I can't go there I can't do that
there's there there's too much there and
and I want to go out and I want to get
it I want to I want to do it better that
when you listen to John and when you
look at his passion yeah this is part of
things I love about him he's he he wants
glory he wants grace he wants it all and
he wants to start tasting it now amen
that drive is something that I as a
Christian minister appreciate in a world
of um settling for crap and so when I
look at John Verve a key and I look at
church planters I don't see a lot of
difference because church planters go
out there and say I've seen problems in
the church and it's been a disaster I'm
gonna finally get church right and they
all fail every one of them
John Verve a key says I want a religion
that isn't a religion I want to I want
to go out there and do things where all
of my experience with
Christianity growing up and paul tillich
until Icahn and the mainline church and
Buddhism nobody got it exactly right and
well here's the thing about John he's
humble he's collaborative he's community
oriented and so I look at this and say
I'm coming with you John me too because
sin is a feature and a bug it's it's a
it's a it's a feature of the church that
has drawn people like John Verve a key
and church planters like what I've had
on my channel Eric jerks in' and says
alright i'm i'm limited by a tradition
but that that limitation is vital
because i know i am small and can't see
a whole lot and so as Chesterton said
i'm gonna give my dead ancestors a seat
at the table so if you follow if you
follow eric Dirksen on twitter he's
always tweeting agustin or crostata or
calvin or you know because our church
fathers because he geez
he knows that there's these these skies
were way smarter than we were and they
knew way more than we know and gosh i
should listen to them but then he's also
paying attention to what's going on in
the culture and I'm doing that with John
John's read books I'll never read John's
dumb things and dabbled with things and
practice things I'll never practice I
don't have enough life in me to
duplicate all of the years that John has
and so get this by listening to John I
can benefit from his sin oh oh am I
saying John's the center yes me too I'm
probably a worst one I I would think
most definitely cuz I know my sins I
don't know his but here's the thing sins
of both John's um transgressions as I
would call them but also his failure to
reach his potential and John is an
honest guy that I'm
don't think I'm saying anything that
would offend him and again this is part
of the reason I love him as a
conversation partner because now John is
so much more gracious than I am and he
would you would be couching these things
and all of his you know all of the great
ways that he does that and I'm I'm an
East Coast boy from New Jersey and I
just boldly Russia and fearfully offend
people and it's probably why I'm such a
bad pastor bad youtuber but I can learn
from John sins if I listen to him
both these categories of sin and so and
I can learn from John's religion that
isn't a religion if I listen to him in
humility because my practice of
Christianity is full of sin both the
lack of potential and the rebellion that
is in me so I don't know if I've
answered your question that was a great
answer golden tip panas has posted his
question he writes hi Paul
I recently just watched a podcast in in
where you mentioned your concepts of God
1 and God too a question that I have is
how do you characterize and
differentiate particular intelligent
design such as natural selection and
central pattern generators versus more
holistic phenomenological Gestalt test
components of God such as the salience
landscape and relevance realization does
the difference lie in a matter of scale
well your your pounding on the door of
the video I hope to make this afternoon
because and this again is where my
conversations with John are so fruitful
because John in a sense and I are
working at the problem from two
different ends I'm coming to it from
Christianity where as Jonathan P Joe
says it's persons all the way up and
John Verve a key is coming at it from
cognitive science which as a scientific
discipline and again there's one thing
I've learned from John it's discipline
in language and
terminology don't equivocate I can hear
him say it you know how many times from
awakening from the meaning crisis okay
so but he's coming at it from the
scientific discipline the spirit of
geometry in which he's practicing a lot
of finesse and and saying okay how
deeply can we penetrate this conundrum
well here's the thing I
if there's anything we've learned about
the universe it's a lot deeper than
we've gone so far we don't know where
the bottom is
in my putting together the PowerPoint
for my video this afternoon I bumped
into a video that I made see I don't
even have time to remember all my old
videos but the the the thumbnail that I
made which I searched for asks this
question this is a video I did in 2019
is personhood detection merely the
perceptual limit of our pattern
recognition I got to read that again is
personhood detection merely the
perceptual limit of our pattern
recognition so part of what we part of
what I saw in the god number one God
number two moment between Jordan
Peterson and Sam Harris was God number
two is clearly personal and Sam is
really I think offended at the notion
that the universe would be owned by a
person I think that's at the heart of
atheism there's an offense in there that
I think it was that Eric Weinstein
Weinstein trying to get my name's right
Eric Weinstein I think perfectly
encapsulated what he said it's better if
there is no God because if there is a
God you have to worry about what's on
his mind
well that's a genius statement and and
with all due respect to the atheists and
the non theists well gosh the the extent
to which if there's a mind a person
behind or three behind the universe the
lengths to which this these people will
go to create involves millions of years
of the death of plants and animals and
human history involves immense amounts
of suffering
oh yeah that's a big question now now
Christians have known this question for
a very long time and weighed it and the
answer they always come up with is sort
of I don't know and I don't know that I
can do the math and that's where it gets
into this lines that I think you nicely
laid out how do you characterize and
differentiate particular intelligent
design and so John verve a key and his
autopoietic and I don't have all those
words really memorized yet all of that
stuff which is sort of going on its own
versus persons which have consciousness
which is sort of this really amazing
field in which the world is too big for
me to know but things can come into my
salience hierarchy and I can in real
time and over time respond to them in
productive ways that pursues different
ends and goals that I possess and choose
yeah so it's a great question I don't
know if I can answer it but that's my
best shot at it
that's great and golden tip pen
responded wow that's a great answer so
he appreciated any other any other
questions I have one that's kind of
focused more on the nature of these dis
cords you know kind of partaking in a
number of these that have popped up you
know Eric Weinstein's comes to mind this
one obviously the bridge is a meaning
server it's hard not to notice that the
bridge is a meaning server has been
around for a good while and has been
able to handle quite well a high level
of disagreement while still largely
staying focused on you know a healthy
form of discussion and it seems to me
that part of that is from people
modeling your behavior on how to have
these types of discussions that you know
you've had with all these random people
and in many ways I've seen John actually
replicate that to some degree with his
voices with verve a key series where he
kind of opens up communication to people
that he wouldn't necessarily agree with
all the way and I was wondering if you
might speak to kind of where you find
that form of discussion and affordance
and how you think it impacts the types
of conversations that are able to occur
in these little groups that have formed
around these various personalities I
come so before before I made videos
about Jordan Peterson and it was just
the Freddy and Paul show on my channel I
was deeply concerned about my own
Christian denomination my own community
so you know some of this goes back to
immigration so one side of my family
were took care of cows and slipped
across the Atlantic
when mr. whiten who was a industrial
magnate in a little town in
Massachusetts all his town all his cows
died in a flu in a cow flu pandemic and
the best cows in the world were from the
Netherlands and the people who were
bringing the cows over were smart enough
to know that hey these there's a real
spirit of finesse surrounding all of
these cows and the people if you want
the best caretakers for the cows get the
cow caretakers who have been developing
the best cows in the world so a bunch of
Friesians
came over with the cows to whitens ville
massachusetts that's my mother's side of
the family my father's side of the
family were Jews and they smuggled over
to Western Michigan and I don't know
what happened but somehow started
assimilating with the Dutch cows farmers
but my great-grandfather was a house
painter so and an artist so he started
he started doing that well so the
Christian Reformed Church has been my
community over time I'm the third
generation of of clergy and my family
and the Christian Reformed Church and I
think it was Martin II Marty who was a
church man who once offered comment on
the Christian Reformed Church and he
it's not a denomination it's an extended
family and that's true less true every
decade but true and I watched my
denomination heading for a fight I
growing up from the 70's 80's 90's Ott's
watched my 230 years I watched my
denomination fight over whether or not
women could serve as deacons elders and
ministers and our denomination was a big
fight and obviously a fight that goes
far beyond my denomination and that
fight cost the denomination dearly a
generation before when my grandmother
was a little girl her sister married the
daughter of one of the guiding lights
and mega church planters of the
Christian Reformed Church at the
beginning of the 20th century herman
hooks a'mma who eventually caused a
schism over this question of the
antithesis and common grace which is
which answers your first question Nick
about pluralism and my my grandmother's
sister was married to the son of Herman
hooks a'mma Homer and a family fight
became a church fight and my my
great-aunt her name was Marie was
shunned because everybody suspected
wrongly that she leaked the family
secret that they were gonna put old
Herman in a home instead of taking care
of him at home and the little sect of of
now secessionists from secessionists
were offended that the family would make
such a decision instead of carrying the
weight of caring for the old
increasingly disabled man at home and
that that wound was a family story that
I heard that got passed on and where
dear old Saint and Marie once tried to
visit her children at the Christian
school and were turned away and so I
watched my denomination and I
watched family split over what roles
women couldn't couldn't have and I'm
watching and I'm watching my
denomination on the verge of having
another civil war over same-sex marriage
and gays and and all of this stuff and
I'm watching the march to war and I'm
troubled because however the war ends
and whoever gets to keep what and
wherever the boundaries lie the wounded
are gonna be all over the battlefield of
my church and I believe that the founder
of my church not Abraham Kuyper not Ben
Rahl T not John Calvin nah Agustin but
Jesus Christ himself did not want his
disciples killing each other over these
ideas
and so that over generations what is a
person to top all the apostate Jacob
that has been built into me this person
whatever a person is that has been built
into me for centuries my Jewish side my
Frisian side and look at those two
pieces of me there's there I can think
of no two groups more stubborn than Jews
and Friesians you know the Friesians
came over with the cows because you know
in cows Friesians met their match in
terms of stubbornness so if some of this
spirit is in me that on one hand on one
side wants the the more nests and the
suchness oh that came from Buddhism oh
no I can't use the term that's a great
idea and John is sort of via the
blessings of secularism sanitized it a
little bit so now a Christian minister
who likes picking other people's
philosophical and theological pockets
and budding into their conversations I
see this I see John verb a key sporting
this and I say I can use that I can that
can that can help me understand glory
and we just put this together this
morning gosh I want to I want to talk to
John Verve a key there's common Grace
and John Verve a key but the antithesis
is still real because the antithesis
provides power for the systems as well
and so I think you said it really well
Nick I want I have my whole life long
have you earned to see churches handle
disagreement and Liat not lose focus on
antithetical things so you know there's
I don't think you could have honored me
in any greater way Nick than the way
that you framed this question because in
many ways
it's the work of my life I want to on
one hand I want us to be honest and
truthful about our sin and and we can't
be honest and truthful about all our sin
it's not appropriate that's that's the
way the world works but sin is a
function of the antithesis but my
Calvinist upbringing says we're all
sinners and in some ways I'm gonna have
more to answer for on Judgment Day then
John Verve a key because I'm a Christian
teacher and I have to own that but I
want a community where people who for
one reason or another say I can't I
can't get on board with the god thing
okay I still want to talk to you Jesus
who founded my religion says love your
neighbor up to and including your rivals
and your enemies now Christians have not
done well with that well they're not
alone in that but that's a standard
Jesus calls me to and so what does that
look like in the midst of this meaning
crisis in the midst of our little corner
of the internet after listening to
Jordan Peterson and watching lights go
on because of that that means going into
spaces like this and creating spaces
like this where where Sam can come in
and say I'm not so sure about that
Trinity thing boy I think it was harder
for people welcoming Sam than whelping
at welcoming atheists but we're learning
that and we're talking to Sam and we're
learning things from Sam and Sam's
learning things from us and we're not
gonna burn them at the stake there's a
little spoiler alert so yeah you come in
if you become my friend you run the risk
of becoming an illustration and poor
Nick knows that too for
cult Nick but uh you know I've got a
little bit of Donald Trump in me too cuz
you know he started as a Frisian Dutch
Reformed guy - so there we have it
Paul banter clean and Donald Trump part
of the same family
boy that'll make some people upset boy
this recording just got a whole lot
spicier well well said Paul Doe very
well son I think that essentially this
this feeling that can come from from
trusting community is what so many
people are missing and whatever routes
and avenues we can come to approach that
and remember it and make it sacred and
and that real sense I think is is what
we have to to enact right to feel a
calling to it and not be afraid to
approach and yeah so for that I greatly
appreciate all this motion that people
are emotions that people are making here
not just yourself but although all the
wonderful people that gather and in
these spots and say these words it's
wonderful
and the other questions see the reason I
leave two hours is because I give long
answers well we definitely appreciate
them so and appreciate your time this is
this has been great
give I'll give a going once going twice
last call well well thank you Paul this
has been fantastic I think I'm gonna
have to listen to this over again
yeah you've given so much there to
listen to it and I love the way you you
you made all your comments relevant to
to this community as well and I know
there's a lot of overlap between this
community in your community but it
certainly to me how how john vicki has
influenced your thinking and I think and
I think probably vice versa that's the
beauty of this right that's what we're
looking for and again John has said that
so well he says you know you have a
conversation both of us leave it
stronger and I think that's you know
Peter Sounion to you know so no it's
it's been wonderful so really appreciate
the opportunity we can do it again
sometime
I posted in the event listening party I
took notes as we went
that helps me when I'm talking and so
yeah I'll probably put this on my
channel I think this would very very
well well that's great so thank you so
much Paul for being here thank you
everyone here I'm continually impressed
by the level and caliber of the
questions of this community and and this
is this is great this is this is what we
want want to see tomorrow at 5:00
Eastern we've got Greg and Rica's who's
going to come by to chat with us
following his voices with fur Becky yeah
so I think that that'll be really
interesting really interesting talk I
hope you all come also Monday to Friday
at 9:30 Eastern we have a listening
party for John's meditation classes and
his meditation sessions and then we and
then we type we sorry we talk we talk
afterwards about our about our our
experience and we might do some lectio
divina that's what's being focused on
for this week so hopefully people you
all will join and again thank you
everyone for coming and we'll we'll
close off the recording and and again
thank you Paul that was fantastic
my pleasure thanks a lot take care
everyone thank you Paul